Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Papers LSC.1243
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carey McWilliams Papers
1930-1940
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.1243
16.5 linear feet (33 boxes. 1 oversize box.)
Carey McWilliams (1905-80) was an attorney with the firm, Black, Hammack and McWilliams in Los Angeles (1927-38), chief of the Division of Immigration and Housing for the State of California (1938-42). McWilliams later worked for The Nation (1945-75). He also wrote numerous books on race and migrant labor issues. The collection consists of research materials, including correspondence, reports, and clippings about migrant farm labor in California and the problems of Mexican Americans.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Randolph and Dora Haynes Foundation, 1952.
The papers form part of the John Randolph Haynes and Dora Haynes Foundation Collections.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942333933606533
Biography
Carey McWilliams was born December 13, 1905 in Steamboat Springs, Colorado; JD, University of Southern California; attorney, Black, Hammack & McWilliams, Los Angeles, 1927-38; chief of Division of Immigration and Housing, State of California, 1938-42; contributing editor, associate editor, and editorial director, The Nation, 1945-55; editor, The Nation, 1955-1975; some of his books include: Ambrose Bierce, a Biography (1929), Factories in the Field: the Story of Migratory Farm Labor in California (1939), Ill Fares the Land: Migrants and Migratory Labor in the United States (1942), Brothers Under the Skin (1943); Prejudice: Japanese-Americans, Symbol of Racial Intolerance (1944), Southern California Country: an Island on the Land (1946), A Mask for Privilege: Anti-Semitism in America (1948), The Education of Carey McWilliams (1979); died June 27, 1980 in New York, New York.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of research materials, including correspondence, reports, and clippings about migrant farm labor in California and the problems of Mexican Americans.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Collection is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Related Material
Carey McWilliams Papers (Collection 1319). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Papers - Card Files (Collection 1243). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Correspondence (Collection 2448). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Collection of materials by and about George Sterling (Collection 276). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Collection of Material about Ambrose Bierce (Collection 277). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams Collection of Material about Mary Hunter Austin (Collection 278). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Carey McWilliams papers (Collection BANC MSS C-H 46). Available at Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.
Carey McWilliams miscellaneous papers. Available at Hoover Institution Archives, Stanford, CA.
The following oral history is available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of Carey McWilliams
Honorable in all things: the memoirs of Carey McWilliams [oral history transcript] / Carey McWilliams, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, c1982. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Items Removed from Collection
Items Removed from Collection
Economic nationalism in Latin America, by Richard F. Behrendt. Albuquerque, University of New Mexico. 1941. (Call no. HC/161/B419).
Employers' liability and workmen's compensation in Arizona, by Victor DeWitt Brannon. Tucson, Arizona, University of Arizona [1934]. (Call no. HD/7816/U7A6/1934a).
The white scourge, by Edward E. Davis. San Antonio, Texas, The Naylor Company, 1940. (Call no. PZ/3/D2921wh).
Demographic and bodily changes in descendants of Mexican immigrants, with comparable data on parents and children in Mexico, by Marcus S. Goldstein. Austin, Texas. Institute of Latin-American studies, University of Texas. 1943. (Call no. GN/58/U5G6).
A place to play in; a survey of youth needs in the southwestern area of Pontiac, Michigan, by Norman Daymond Humphrey. Pontiac southwest community center. 1946. (Call no. [?]Q/796/P).
Report and recommendations. Interdepartmental Rio Grande Committee. Washington, U.S. Department of Agriculture. 1937. (Call no. HD/1694/A4i).
Mexican war workers in the United States; the Mexico-United States manpower recruiting program and its operation, by Robert C. Jones. Washington, Pan American Union, Division of Labor and Social Information. 1945. (Call no. HD/8081/M6J6).
Spanish-speaking children in Texas, by Wilson Little. Austin, University of Texas Press. 1944. (Call no. F/786/L).
Child labor in agriculture and farm life in the Arkansas Valley of Colorado; based upon studies made during summer, fall, and winter, 1924, in cooperation with the National child labor committee, by Bertram H. Mautner and W. Lewis Abbott, assisted by Harold. W. Bell and Anne Bispham. Colorado Springs, Colorado College. 1929. (Call no. HD/6250/U7/C6m).
Old Spain in new America, by Robert McLean. Issued by the Council of Women for Home Missions. New York, Associated Press, c. 1946. (Call no. BV/2788/S7M3).
Teresita of the valley, by Florence Crannell Means. Boston, Houghton Mifflin Company (Riverside Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts) 1943. (Call no. PZ/7/M5124/Te).
In support of fair employment practice; a history of four years of activities of the Metropolitan Detroit Fair Employment Practice Council, January 1942-December 1945. Metropolitan Detroit Fair Employment Practice Council. Detroit, Michigan. 1945. (Call no. HD/6476/D6).
We who are America, by Kenneth Dexter Miller. New York, Friendship Press. 1943. (Call no. E/184/AlM53).
Sleep in the sun, by Alan B. Moody. Boston, Houghton Mifflin Company. 1945. (Call no. PZ/3/M772S1).
The Spanish speaking of the southwest and west (second report) Washington, D.C., National Catholic welfare conference, September of Social Action. 1944. (Call no. F/786/N372).
A study of the negroes of Tuscon, Arizona, conducted for an interracial committee... Eugene T. Lies, Survey director. December 1945-February 1946. (Call no. HT/1583T).
Labor trends and social welfare in Latin America, 1939-1940. Washington, Pan American Union - Division of Labor and Social Information. 1941. (Call no. HD/6957/P187).
Bibliography on Labor and social welfare in Latin America. Washington, Pan American Union. 1940. (Call no. Z/7164/LlP25).
Racial influences in the mental and physical development of Mexican children, by Franklin C. Pascal and Louis R. Sullivan. Baltimore, Williams & Wilkins. 1925. (Call no. BF/431/P3).
It happened in Taos, by Jesse T. Reid. Albuquerque, University of New Mexico Press. 1946. (Call no. HN/79/N6/R2).
A summary of the sessions on housing, health, nutrition, public assistance and recreation, July 6-9, 1943. Institute of Inter-American problems in the Rocky Mountain region. (Call no. HV/88/R6).
Culture of a contemporary rural community: El Cerrito, New Mexico, by Olen Leonard and C.P. Loomis. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Agricultural Economics. Washington, D.C. 1941. no.1. (Call no. *HN/79/N6/L3).
Central Valley project studies. The war program, problems 1-5. Washington, Government Printing Office. 1947. (Call no. TC/24/C2A55).
The Colorado river. 1946. A comprehensive report on the development of the water resources of the Colorado River basin for irrigation, power production, and other beneficial uses in Arizona, California, Nevada, New Mexico, Utah and Wyoming... Sponsored and prepared under the general supervision of the Bureau of Reclamation, Washington. (Call no. TC/425/C6A3/1946a).
Protection and development of lower Colorado River Basin. Government Printing Office. 1924. Information presented to the committee in the House of Representatives, 68th Congress, 1st session, H.R. 2903, by Mr. Swing... Hearings before the Federal Power Commission and other matters relating to the development of the Colorado River. (Call no. TC/425/C6A3/1924).
Consolidated progress report of the Mexican farm labor transportation program of the FSA through November 20, 1942. San Francisco, California, [1942]. (Call no. HD/8081/A1M6).
Material on the partido system. U.S. Forest Service. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. SF/371/N6).
Notes on community-owned land grants in New Mexico. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. HD/243/N6).
Proposals for the Santa Cruz area. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1935. (Call no. HD/1516/N6sc).
A report on the Cuba valley. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. HD/1516/N6c).
Tenant herding in the Cuba valley. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. SF/371/N6c).
Tewa basin study, 1935. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Division of Economic Surveys. Albuquerque, New Mexico. vol.1: The Indian pueblos. vol.2: The Spanish-American villages. (Call no. HD/1501/N6t).
Tijeras Canyon - Moriarty area. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. HD/1516/N6t).
Village dependence on migratory labor in the Upper Rio Grande area. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Section of Human Surveys. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. HD/1527/N6).
Villanueva, a San Miguel county village. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Region 8. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1938. (Call no. HD/1516/N6v).
Handling of a cash crop (chili) in the Tewa Basin. U.S. Soil Conservation Service, Southwest Region. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1937. (Call no. SB/320/U58h).
Rural rehabilitation in New Mexico. Albuquerque, New Mexico. 1935. (Call no. HD/1516/N6r).
Zoot Suiters (Includes California Governor's Citizen Committee, Report and Recommendations. 1943). (Call no. HV6439 U5 L89m. Available in Microfilm and media service.).
Mexican American migrant agricultural laborers -- California.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; McWilliams, Carey -- Archives
- Adamic, Louis
  - Adamic, Louis. (Box 26)
    Scope and Contents note
    Correspondence to...concerning Mexicans.
- Agriculture
  - The Agricultural Situation. Bureau of Agricultural Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture., May-December 1939.; vol.23 no.5-12. (Box 1)
  - The Agricultural Situation. Bureau of Agricultural Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture., January-December 1940.; vol.24 no.1-12. (Box 1)
  - The Agricultural Situation. Bureau of Agricultural Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture., January-December 1941.; vol.25 no.1-12. (Box 1)
  - The Agricultural Situation. Bureau of Agricultural Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture., January-August, October 1942.; vol.26 no.1-8, 10. (Box 1)
  - The Agricultural Situation. Bureau of Agricultural Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture., January-April 1943.; vol.27 no.1, 4. (Box 1)
- Agriculture - Economic Aspects
  - Central California Beet Growers Association, Limited. The sugar market., June 1938. (Box 1)
    Clippings, periodical articles, reports and other material on growers' organizations, financial return of agriculture, etc.
- Agriculture - Kansas
  - The effect of the combined harvester-thresher on farm organization in southwestern Kansas and northwestern Oklahoma, by W.E. Grimes. Manhattan, Kansas. Agricultural Experiment station., July 1928.; 24pp. (Circular 142). (Box 1)
- Agriculture - Mechanization
  - The production tools of agriculture, an address by Harry G. Davis before 40th annual convention, Arkansas Hardware & Implement Association, Little Rock, Arkansas., February 20, 1940. (Box 1)
  - How farm machinery creates employment., June 20, 1934. (Box 1)
    A symposium of papers and discussions presented before the Power and Machinery Division of the 28th annual meeting of the Society held at Detroit, Michigan.
  - Technological progress in American farming. Statement by Fowler McCormick. before the Temporary National Economic Committee (76th Congress), Washington, D.C., April 24, 1940. (Box 1)
  - Some aspects of mechanization in American economy, by Harry G. Davis., March 1940. (Box 1)
    Reprinted from Agricultural Engineering.
  - The economics of farm machinery, by Dr. John Lee Coulter., July 1940. (Box 1)
  - [Reprints, articles concerning influence of machines on farm labor and the nature of farm labor itself]. (Box 1)
  - Technological progress in American farming, with forward by S.G. McAllister, President International Harvester Company ?)., (1937 (Box 1)
- Agriculture - North Dakota
  - Agricultural Experiment Station Bimonthly bulletin., May 1939. (Box 1)
    (Relationship of farm population movement and drought). vol.1 no.5.
- Agriculture - Reports - Miscellaneous
  - Transient and migratory workers., 2pp. (Box 19)
  - Agricultural labor housing survey., 2pp. (Box 19)
- Agriculture - Texas
  - Some technological changes in the high plains cotton area of Texas, by Bonnen, C.A. & Magee, A.C., August 1938.; Reprinted from Journal of Farm Economics, vol.20 no.3. (Box 1)
  - Some technological changes in the high plains cotton area of Texas, by C.A. Bonnen., August 1938. (Box 1)
    Reprinted from Journal of Farm Economics, vol.20 no.3.
- Agriculture - Unions in Agriculture
  - Agricultural Bulletin. Washington, D.C., National Council to Aid Agricultural Workers., November 15, 1939-August 1940.; vol.1 no.1-4. (Box 21)
- Agriculture - U.S.
  - Chemurgy and the grapes of promise, by Louis J. Taber. 6th Annual National Farm Chemurgic Conference. Chicago., March 27-29, 1940. (Box 1)
  - Material on increasing the industrial uses of farm products or chemurgy. Reports on conditions of agriculture and the farmer. (Box 1)
  - The Llano Del Rio cooperative colony (in Antelope Valley, Los Angeles County, California-a cooperative colony). Hanna, Hugh S. (Box 1)
  - Agriculture and banking, by C.B. Jennett. Sixth annual National Farm Chemurgic Conference, Chicago., March 27-29, 1940. (Box 1)
  - Industrial utilization of farm products and the proposed establishment of a western division of the National Research Council. Winnipeg, The North-west Line Elevators Association. (Box 1)
  - Farmers and Farm Workers, prepared by Farm Research, Incorporated. Washington, D.C. Labor Fact Book 3, New York International Publishers. Library of Congress [call no.] HD 8072 L253., 1936. (Box 1)
    Chapter 7, p.121.
  - Some possible effects of the war on American agriculture, by N.R. Whitney ... at the Second Mid-American Chemurgic Conference, Cleveland, Ohio., September 16-17, 1940.; 2 copies. (Box 1)
  - The agricultural history of Iowa as a field of research, by Louis Bernard Schmidt., October 1939.; (Reprinted from Agricultural History, vol.13 pp.218-220). (Box 1)
- Aliens - Drive Against
  - [Newspaper clippings, articles, etc.]. (Box 1, Box 2)
    General note
    SEE: Bridges, Harry
- The Americas
  - The Americas. (Box 26)
    A review of Latin American news published fort-nightly by the council for Pan American democracy.
- Anthropology
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- Anti-Semitism
  - Articles, clippings, etc. (Box 2)
- Arizona
  - Reports on condition of farm labor. (Box 2)
- Associated Farmers
  [SEE: United States. Congress, 74th. Senate. Committee on education and labor. Subcommittee on Senate resolution 266.]
  - [Folder of newspaper clippings]. (Box 3)
  - Typed copies from newspaper clippings from Washington New Dealer, Seattle, Washington., November 24, 1939-December 14, 1939. (Box 3)
  - Report on Associated Farmers of California, Incorporated; its structure, aims and activities ... submitted to Professor Eric C. Bellquist, instructor, Political Science 114. University of California, Berkeley., April 18, 1938. (Box 2)
- Ayres, Duran Ed
  - Ayres report., August 10, 1942. (Box 26)
    (Another copy in Mexicans - Juvenile Delinquency)
- The Battle of Camp San Vicente
  - Photos and a statement by Carey McWilliams. (Box 26)
- Bibliographies
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- Birth Control
  - Birth control in a midwestern city and Contraceptive service in three areas, by Regime K. Stix. (Box 3)
- Books
  - Ill fares the land. Book 2., Clippings, [notes, digests of periodical articles,] articles, letters on migrant labor. (Box 5)
  - Ill fares the land. Book (miscellaneous)., Reports, newspaper clippings on treatment of agricultural workers. Some material on Associated farmers. (Box 3)
- Bridges, Harry R.
  SEE: Aliens - Drive Against
- California
  - Governor's Citizen Committee Report and Recommendation on the outbreaks of violence in Los Angeles during the week of June 6, 1943. n.p., June 12, 1943.; 7 leaves, Mimeograph. (Box 26)
    SEE: Zoot Suiters in Carey McWilliams Collection (no.1319)
  - Report and Recommendations of the Citizens Committee, June 12, 1943. n.p. (Box 4)
    Governor's Citizens Committee to Investigate the Outbreaks of Violence in Los Angeles, 1943.
    See: Cary McWilliams Collection (no.1319). Zoot Suiters on microfilm (Film HV/6439/U5/L87m)
- California Anti-Migrant Law
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- California - Department of Agriculture
  - California Department of Agricultural Reports on acreage from Agricultural Commissioners of the counties., Clippings and bulletins. (Box 4)
- California Chamber of Commerce
  - Handbook on sources of economic data pertaining to California: state agencies., 1939. (Box 4)
  - Speeches before, studies by California Chamber of Commerce on the subject of farm labor. (Box 4)
- California Chinese Press
  - California Chinese Press 11 Colombus Avenue, San Francisco, California., November 29, 1940-May 9, 1941; June 6, August 1, 1941.; vol.1 no.4-13, 16-19, 24-25; vol.2 no.3, 11. (Box 4)
- California - Department of Industrial Relations
  - Analysis of proposed reductions in the budget. (Box 4)
- California Department of Industrial Relations - Division of Immigration and Housing
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
  - Review of personnel changes., 1939-1940. (Box 4)
  - Housing for migratory agricultural labor, by L.T. Mott [and] F.J. Rugg. (Box 4)
- California - University of California
  - Studies published by the University on agricultural labor. (Box 4)
- California Farm Reporter
  - California Farm Reporter (December 11, 1941, January-May; August-December 1942). (Box 4)
    vol.1-Santa Clara, California. California farm research and legislative committee. vol.1, vol.2 no.1-5, 8-12.
- California History
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- Cannery Field Workers News
  - Cannery Field Workers News. 23 SW Sherman St., Portland, Oregon., August 24, 1942.; vol.4 no.47. (Box 4)
- Central Idea
  - Central Idea. Published by Central Junior High School. (Box 26)
- Central Valley Project
  - Radio address, by Frank W. Clark, director, Department of public works, Sacramento, California, 6:45 to 7:00 p.m., KFBK., February 13, 1941. (Box 4)
  - Central Valley development and its relation to transportation, by Culbert L. Olson. Address to the Pacific Transportation Association at the Commercial Club, San Francisco, California., January 21, 1941. (Box 4)
- The Challenge to Democracy
  - Iowa State College, Agricultural Experiment Station, Ames, Iowa., June and October 1941. (Box 5)
- Civil Liberties
  - Pamphlets, newspaper clippings, etc., 2 folders. (Box 5)
  - Civil Rights Bulletin. National Federation for Constitutional Liberties. Washington, D.C., March 1942. (Box 5)
- Civil Rights
  - Statement of Citizen's Committee, Los Angeles. (Box 26)
- Committee to Aid Agricultural Organization
  - Letters, reports, miscellaneous material in regard to this group and John Steinbeck committee., [Includes a] note from John Steinbeck [Handwritten]. (Box 5)
- Committee to Aid Agricultural Workers
  - [Miscellaneous material; several letters to CMcW.]. (Box 5)
- Cooperative Crop Reporting Service
  - Similar reports by California Cooperative crop reporting service., May 1938, April 1939. (Box 5)
    Commercial vegetable crops: California.
- Cooperative Movement - China
  - Two years of indusco, by Rewi Alley, (1940). (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets, periodicals, and mimeographed article. (Box 5)
  - Appeal., May 1939. (Box 2)
    Chinese Industrial Co-operatives. Hong Kong, China.
  - INDUSCO News. Hong Kong, China., November 1, 1940.; no.31. (Box 5)
  - New Defence: A Journal of the 30,000 Industrial Co-operatives Movement of China. Chungking, China., May 1939.; vol.1 no.2. (Box 5)
- Correspondence to Carey McWilliams
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
    Some deals with proposal to Nelson Rockefeller.
    SEE: Latin American Relations Proposal, 1941
- Cotton
  - Material on wages, prices, etc. (Box 5)
  - Power farming and labor displacement in the cotton belt, 1937... U.S. Department of Labor, Bureau of Labor Statistics. Washington, D.C., U.S. Government Printing Office., 1938.; Parts 1 and 2, Serial no. R 737. (Box 5)
- Criminal Syndicalism - Sacramento
  - Letters, pamphlets, newspaper and periodical clippings concerning the trial., 1935. (Box 6)
- Cultural Relations
  - Cultural Relations between the United States and Latin America. (Box 26)
- Dairying
  - Labor and other factors influencing dairy production in the Los Angeles milkshed, November 1942. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Bureau of Agricultural Economics. Washington, D.C., February 1943. (Box 6)
- Dies Committee
  - Pamphlets, letters, and other material concerning work of. (Box 6)
- Disaster Ordinances., ca. 1938
  - Newspaper clippings, etc. on preparations and organization for major disaster, (ca. 1938). (Box 6)
- Economics
  - Modern economic trends, lecture by Dr. Ira B. Cross. Labor Relations College, lecture no.2. Berkeley, University of California., March 20, 1940. (Box 6)
- Employers' Organizations (Miscellaneous)
  - [Folder of newspaper clippings and articles]. (Box 6)
- Eugenics
  - Social environment as a modifying factor in the correlation between maternal age and intelligence of offspring, by Pearl Moshinsky., January 1942.; Reprinted from the Milbank Memorial Fund Quarterly, vol.20 no.1. (Box 6)
- Factories in the field
  - Factories in the field. (Box 6)
    Letters, notes, copy of The Kaweah Commonwealth and other material about Kaweah and Fort Romie colony.
- Facts and Figures
  - Facts and Figures. California C.I.O. Research Department of the California State Industrial Union Council, San Francisco., January-February 1943.; vol.2 no.1. (Box 6)
- Facts for Farmers
  - Facts for Farmers: A Journal for Progressive Farmers. 39 Cortlandt St., New York., July-September 1941; May 1937.; vol.1 no.1-3; vol.3 no.5, pp.7-8. (Box 6)
- Fair Employment Practice Committee
  - [No further description available]. (Box 26)
- The Farm Workers' Association
  SEE: Monroe, Lillian
  - [No further description available]. (Box 16)
- Fascism (in General)
  - The American Citizen. San Rafael, California, Henry R. Sanborn., January 17, 1936-July 15, 1936.; vol.1, vol.2 no.1-2, 4-7, 9, 12. (Box 5, Box 6)
  - [Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, etc.]. (Box 6)
- Fecundity
  - McCleary, G.F. Australia population problem. (Box 7)
  - Beebe, Gilbert W. Differential fertility by color for coal miners in Logan County, West Virginia. (Box 7)
  - Vance, Rupert. Regional approach to the study of high fertility. (Box 7)
  - Kiser, Clyde V., Social implications of the under-developed family. (Box 7)
  - Beebe, Gilbert W. Differential fertility by color for coal miners in Logan County, West Virginia. (Box 7)
  - Vance, Rupert. Regional approach to the study of high fertility. (Box 7)
  - Kiser, Clyde V., Social implications of the underdeveloped family. (Box 7)